<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Great Yarmouth, vpon VVednesday, the 12. of September. 1599. by W. Y. The argument whereof was chosen to minister instructions vnto the people, vpon occasion of those present troubles, which then were feared by the Spaniards.</title>
            <author>Younger, William, b. 1572 or 3.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125585</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900654</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900654</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132778</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132778)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2088:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Great Yarmouth, vpon VVednesday, the 12. of September. 1599. by W. Y. The argument whereof was chosen to minister instructions vnto the people, vpon occasion of those present troubles, which then were feared by the Spaniards.</title>
                  <author>Younger, William, b. 1572 or 3.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[87] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Simon Stafford, dwelling on Adling hill, neere Carterlane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Yonger.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Jeremiah IV, 14 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132778:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132778:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at great Yarmouth, <hi>Vpon VVedneſday, the</hi> 12. <hi>of</hi> September. 1599.</p>
            <p>By W. Y.</p>
            <p>The argument whereof was choſen to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter inſtructions vnto the people, vpon occaſion of thoſe preſent troubles, which then were feared by the Spaniards.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 9.18.</hi>
               </bibl> Better is Wiſdome, then weapons of warre: but one ſinner deſtroyeth much good.</q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Simon Stafford, dwelling on</hi> Adling hill, neere Carter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane. 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:132778:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132778:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, Maſter Iohn <hi>Felton the elder, and Maſter</hi> Thomas Manfield, Bayliffes of the Towne of great Yarmouth, grace and peace in our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is fayned of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets (Worſhipfull maſter Bayliffes,
<note place="margin">Ouid. Metam. 11. Riuus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, &amp;c.</note> that there is a Riuer in Hell called <hi>Lethe,</hi> of which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer drinketh, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets al that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred before. Whatſoeuer they haue imagined, ſure it is, that the diuell hath an helliſh deuice, to make the eares of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple drunken with vanities, that whatſoeuer inſtructions haue beene deliuered vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet, for the moſt part, they are ſoone forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and the remembrance of them no more to be found. I will not condemne them for ſo weake of memorie, as <hi>Maſsula</hi> was, who forgot his owne name: or ſo dull of capacitie, as the <hi>Thracians,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:132778:3"/>could not recko<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue foure, yet ſure it is, the ſmall profite and practiſe that ariſeth by the preaching of the word, argueth the dryneſſe of their brains, or that God ſpeaks once and twiſe, and man regardes it not. Many there be which will goe to heare ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, but few that can goe to remember them: could wee as well remember, as wee can heare, no doubt, Chriſtianitie would flouriſh as the vine-tree, and bring forth plenty of fruit: but becauſe it is otherwiſe, ſermons being once preached, become as muſicke vnto vs, delighting our eares onely for a time: but being ended, their ſound vaniſheth away. Therefore (though I may ſeeme to adde more fulnes to the ſea) I haue publiſhed, and in publiſhing, enlarged this ſermon, which was once preached before you, that if your memory faile of that which was then deliuered, the eare may heare it again, and the eye ſee it, and the mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, and the ſoule receiue and taste the benefite thereof:
<note place="margin">Efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> litera, Barnard, Ep. 66.</note> and though it bee now leſſe perſwaſiue, then when it was pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the geſture and countenance of a liuing man: yet wants there not to anſwere it, that you may reade and read it againe, meditating thereon not once or twiſe, but
<pb facs="tcp:132778:3"/>often. Many wiſe and learned haue pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and painefully laboured in this courſe, and the world floweth with diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Bookes, as the ſea with varietie of fiſhes, and therefore mine might haue well beene ſpared: yet was the argument (of which Iſpake) ſo fitting to the time when I ſpake, that leſt we ſhould be as forgetfull of theſe inſtructions, as it ſeemes wee are of thoſe rumors of warres and troubles which then ſodainely befell vs, I haue ventured to acquaint you with the ſame matter againe, and to make the benefite thereof more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, which then was but priuate to your owne eares.</p>
            <p>Now, becauſe you are the men, whom the Lord hath made his lieutenants ouer this towne, next vnder her Maieſtie,
<note place="margin">Num. 27.17.</note> to goe in and out before this people: I haue made you the patrons of this my ſimple labour, as you are Patrons ouer thoſe (for whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit it was preached, and is now publiſhed) <hi>both to leade them forth, and to bring them home, that the congregation of the Lord, might not bee as ſheep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſhepheard.</hi> And euen as the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone doth by a ſecret operation and vertue attract yron vnto it, ſo your vertuous and
<pb facs="tcp:132778:4"/>religious minds, entertaining and patroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing this, may (with the Loadſtone) draw others of the iron ſort, and thoſe of baſer mettall then your ſelues, to entertaine, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, and peruſe it, to their comfort, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing garded with the countenance and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite of your names. If any Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue profite by it,
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> let him, who is the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights, and giuer of euerie good and perfect gift,</hi> and the encreaſe of theſe which are vnperfite, haue the prayſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; there ſhall none of his glorie cleaue to my fingers: neither is that which I haue done, for any earthly reſpect, or worldly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: for I haue had that which I expect, and more I neither looke for, nor deſire. Onely this, that the Lord in his mercy would grant,
<note place="margin">Oculus &amp; ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum. Emble<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac. quo Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regimen deſig. Pſa. 2.9</note> that as he hath ſet you on high, and graced you with the gouernment of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: ſo your <hi>eye</hi> &amp; your <hi>ſcepter</hi> may be ioyned together: that firſt you may be <hi>quick-ſighted</hi> to diſcerne ſinne, and ſin being diſcouered, to bruiſe it in peeces with your <hi>ſcepter</hi> of gouernement, that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may prayſe you in the gate, and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice aduaunce her ſelfe in the great congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: that vnity, peace, and concord may be eſtabliſhed, vertue, godlines, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb facs="tcp:132778:4"/>furthered: that the preaching of the word may more and more flouriſh, &amp; worke mightily in the harts of the people for their conuerſion:
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.13.</note> and that <hi>Yarmouth</hi> may be with
<note n="*" place="margin">So the word ſignifies.</note> Capernaum, euen <hi>a place of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> ſcituate by the ſeaſide.</p>
            <p>The Lord, euen the moſt mightie God, inflame your worſhipfull &amp; zealous hearts with a care hereof, that during <hi>the heate of the day,</hi> and the time of your gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ye may be Paragons to thoſe which went before, and examples to as many as ſhall follow. And thus I commend you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, and to the <hi>word of his grace,</hi> which is able to build you further, and to giue you an heauenly inheritance, among them which are ſanctified in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. From the Priory in <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> Oct. <hi>24. 1599.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your VVorships in the Lord, <hi>William Yonger.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:132778:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132778:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT great Yarmouth.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>The Text. <hi>Ieremiah 4.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>O Ieruſalem, waſh thine heart from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, that thou maiſt be ſaued: how long ſhall thy wicked thoughts remaine within thee?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He purpoſe of the Prophet in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie (Worſhipfull and well beloued) is to worke conuerſion in the hearts of the Iewes:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.12.</note> and becauſe (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayes) <hi>A three-fold coard is not eaſily broken:</hi> ſo to the end that hee might with greater force, &amp; more vehemencie, draw them
<pb facs="tcp:132778:6"/>thereunto, hee hath twiſted and twy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together a three-fold cord, an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of a triple force and efficacie, to moue them to repentance. Firſt, from the conſideration of his benefits and mercies beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, in the ſecond and third verſes of the ſecond Chapter. Secondly, from couenants and promiſes made vnto them, in the fourteenth verſe of the former Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Thirdly, from iudgements and threatnings denounced againſt them, in the ſeuenth verſe of this Chapter, where the Prophet ſaith:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>The Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is come vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his den, the deſtroyer of the Gentiles is departed and gone forth, to lay the land waſte, and the Cities ſhal be deſtroyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> So that you ſee how wiſely, &amp; with what powerful diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the prophet enforceth his exhortation.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 From benefits beſtowed:</item>
               <item>2 From promiſes made:</item>
               <item>3 From iudgements threatned.</item>
            </list>
            <p>So as, if benefits would not allure them, promiſes may prouoke them: if promiſes could not prouoke them, iudgements might feare them: when <hi>Nabucadnezzar</hi> ſhould come as a ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:132778:6"/>Lion from his den, and their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the Caldea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to lay the land waſte, and to leuell their Cities with the ground, when places full of inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, ſhould bee left without inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, when all the orders and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Iſrael, from the higheſt Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, to the loweſt ſhrub, from the Prince of high eſtate, vnto the man of low degree: when the heart of the king ſhould periſh within him, and the hearts of their nobles languiſh: their prieſts aſtoniſhed, and their Prophets wonder: when the habitations of Sion ſhould bee burnt with the fire of the enemie, and the ſtreetes of Ieruſalem ſcowred with the iudgements of the almightie: when they thought ſtill to haue enioyed peace, the ſword ſhould pierce their fleſh, and when they had ſwallowed vp aboundance, by reaſon of peace, they ſhould wallow in the bloud of their owne deſtruction. I ſay, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al this, as ſodain as a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt, as ſwift as a flying Eagle, ſhould come vpon them, then ſhould they confeſſe their own wo, &amp; profeſſe their own deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Wo be to vs, for we are deſtroyed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.</note>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:132778:7"/>
            <p>Wherfore, as the Prophet had ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before in the 1, 4, &amp; 8. verſes, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for their conuerſion: ſo likewiſe, in this verſe which I haue read vnto you, <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh thine hart from wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that thou maiſt bee ſaued: how long ſhall thy wicked thoughts remaine within thee?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, The Lord hath a quarrell againſt thee, O Ieruſalem, he hath ſharpened the arrowes of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, hee hath bent his bow and made it readie: the inſtruments of his wrath, and engines of his indignation, are prouided for thy deſtruction: <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> and the Caldaeans are in leſſe then an houres warning to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his commaund, they ſtay but for the Lords watch-word, to ſay vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Goe, and they goe; Kill, and they ſhal deuoure: thy caſe being thus, there is no other remedie to bee had, or courſe to bee taken for thy ſafetie, but this: <hi>Waſh thy heart from wickednes, O Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words (as you ſee) doe contain nothing elſe,
<note place="margin">Diuiſio.</note> but an exhortation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and in it I obſerue theſe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:132778:7"/>
               <item>1 The exhortation it ſelfe.</item>
               <item>2 The reaſon of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The exhortation it ſelfe, in theſe words: <hi>O Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe, that thou maiſt bee ſaued.</hi> The reaſon, in the wordes following: <hi>How long ſhal thy wicked thoughts remain within thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the exhortation it ſelfe, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound three poynts to bee handled:
<list>
                  <item>1 The perſon exhorted: <hi>O Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 The thing required: <hi>Waſh thine heart from wickednes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 The end: <hi>that thou maiſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the reaſon or argument, vttered by way of complaint, theſe fiue things offer themſelues to our conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The circumſtance of time, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the argument is enforced: <hi>How long?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quovſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The thing which hee complaines of: not actions or words, which are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcerned, but <hi>thoughts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 The qualities of theſe thoughts: they are not of any holy and ſanctified diſpoſition, but they are <hi>wicked.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Impiae.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 The continuance: for they haue
<pb facs="tcp:132778:8"/>not their motions and flittings, as the wind in the ayre, which is ſometime in the Eaſt, and ſometime in the weſt, but they abide by it,
<note place="margin">Manent.</note> they <hi>remaine.</hi> Fiftly, the place of their abode, is not in any place about,
<note place="margin">In medio tui.</note> or without vs, but <hi>within.</hi> Of theſe in order: and firſt, for the firſt, that is, the perſon exhorted.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>O Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>Almightie God made a law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.10. that no Citie ſhould be deſtroyed,
<note place="margin">First per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted.</note> before peace were offered vnto it, <hi>When thou commeſt neere a Citie to fight againſt it, thou ſhalt offer it peace:</hi> and wee reade in the ſecond of <hi>Samuel,</hi> 20. that the prudent and prouident woman of <hi>Abel,</hi> obiected this law to <hi>Ioab,</hi> in effect, when hee had caſt vp a Mount againſt the Citie. That ſpeech of our Sauiour Chriſt, vnto the Cities of Corayſin and Bethſayda, giues vs to to vnderſtand, that there were many notable things wrought in them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the woe tooke hold vpon them. So the Lord here threatning Iudah and Ieruſalem, with the ſword of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,
<pb facs="tcp:132778:8"/>that the ſcouts came from a farre countrey, to compaſſe it round about, as the watch-men in the field, for the vtter ſubuerſion and deſolation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: yet hee offers peace vnto it. The Prophet comes to Ieruſalem, with a ſentence of ſafetie in his mouth, as <hi>Noahs</hi> doue came to the Arke, with an Oliue branch in her bill.</p>
               <p>If a man ſhould weigh the iuſtice of GOD in a ballance, and narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he examine it, hee ſhall neuer ſee it his maner, to puniſh any place, or plague any people, without iuſt cauſe: for, though hee lookes, for a time, with a ſierce countenance, and threatens to ſend downe his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as thunder-bolts, and his wrath as a mightie tempeſt, to ſeaze vpon the wicked: yet hee powres downe a ſweete ſhowre of his mercie before, ſo as, if there bee any inſight or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in them, of Gods hand that hangs ouer them, they may preuent it. The Lord heere proclaimes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen warre againſt his people: yet the Prophet deliuers vnto them many good exhortations aforehande, as
<pb facs="tcp:132778:9"/>
                  <hi>Ionathan</hi> ſhotte arrowes, to giue <hi>Dauid</hi> warning, that by repentance they might preuent his iudgements. <hi>O Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, waſh thine heart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wickednes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame loue (beloued) which the Lord in former times bare to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> and to the Cities of <hi>Iudah,</hi> is like to the lawes of the Medes &amp; Perſians,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.</note> which are neuer altered, but euer, and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer are continued: and his mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his people, riſeth vp by degrees, like the water in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezec.</hi> 4.7.</note> which at the firſt time came but to the anckles, the ſecond time to the knees, the third time to his loynes, the fourth time it was as a deepe riuer, and not to be paſſed ouer; for the further hee waded, the deeper hee was plunged: ſo Gods loue is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrutabile quiddam,</hi> a thing vnſearchea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; his mercie paſt finding out. And if euer age in former and precedent times had experience of it, if euer <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> and the Cities of <hi>Iudah</hi> had a taſte of it, if euer the ſweete ſhowres of <hi>Manna</hi> rained downe vpon the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites; ſurely the ſweete ſhowres of his mercie haue plentifully beene powred downe vpon vs, and his loue hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced
<pb facs="tcp:132778:9"/>vs on euerie ſide. For God is not delighted in the deſtruction of a ſinner: he takes no pleaſure to ſee the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of his owne handes, and the children (as I may ſay) of his owne loynes, murdered and maſſacred in the ſtreetes, by the ſword of the enemie: and hence it is, that the Lord in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, and at ſundrie times, by the mouthes of his Prophets, hath vſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations euen without number, to diſſwade them from the cauſe of Gods iudgements, that is, from ſinne, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and tranſgreſsion. Eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the beginning of this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <hi>Ieremie</hi> hath beene very earneſt: as in the third Chapter, the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth Iſrael for an harlot. <hi>Lift vp thine eyes, Oh Iſrael, vnto the high places, ſee and behold if thou haſt not playd the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, &amp;c.</hi> Thou haſt ſitten wayting for them in the wayes, as the Arabian in the wilderneſſe: yea, the land is polluted with thy whoredomes and abominations: yet, when Iſrael had done all this, God ſayde, <hi>Turne vnto mee:</hi> notwithſtanding, ſhee returned not, as her rebellious ſiſter <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132778:10"/>ſaw. Againe, in the fourteenth verſe: <hi>O ye diſobedient children, turne vnto me, and I will take you, one of a Citie, and</hi> 2. <hi>of a tribe, and wil bring you into Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and I will giue you paſtors according to mine owne heart, that ſhall feed you with wiſedome and vnderſtanding.</hi> The like in the 22. verſe, and in many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: the Lord ſeemes to bee mooued with a pitifull compaſsion and commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration ouer his owne people: their caſe was pitifull in his ſight, and their careleſſe regard wrought ſorrow in his heart, when he ſaw that howſoeuer he was prouident for their ſaluation, yet were they verie forward in their owne deſtruction: and the more carefull he he was for their conuerſion, the leſſe reſpect had they to his admonition.</p>
               <p>Indeede true it is an auncient father ſayth, The wicked <hi>alacrius currunt ad mortem, quàm nos ad vitam:</hi> they runne farre faſter in the way to condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then the godly doe in the way to ſaluation: as the Pſalmiſt notes them for their haſte, when hee deſcribes the vngodly, as if they had wings on their heeles: <hi>Their feete are ſwift to
<pb facs="tcp:132778:10"/>ſhed bloud.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 145.</note> Yet the Lord (who as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſayth) is <hi>merciful, gracious, long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and of great goodnes,</hi> laboureth to draw them home: his heart breakes within him, and his bowels yearne with griefe, when he ſees Ieruſalem: that is to ſay, his own people, how wilful they are in their owne deſtruction. <hi>As I liue</hi> (ſayth the Lord) <hi>I will not the death of a ſinner:</hi> As if he ſhould ſay: The fault is not mine, when ſinners drinke the dregges of iniquitie, when the ſcourge of my iudgements faſten vpon them: for I haue no pleaſure to ſee the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of mine owne hands periſh in confuſion: <hi>As I liue, as I liue</hi> (ſayth the Lord) <hi>I will not the death of a ſinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marcellus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Valerius.</note> after his ſouldiers had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <hi>Syracuſa,</hi> not without the great ſlaughter of many, was ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſsionate ouer them, that he went vp to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt towre in the Caſtle, and with teares lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the ruine &amp; ouerthrow therof. <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeaks of one <hi>Pollio</hi> a Romane, who hauing inuited the Emperor <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> to a feaſt, would haue thrown his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into a deep poole in his rage, for a ſmal matter. The Emperor beholding
<pb facs="tcp:132778:11"/>his angrie ſpirit, controlde him with theſe words, <hi>Homo cuiuſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, &amp;c.</hi> A man, of what ſtate or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoeuer he bee, if there were no other cauſe, but becauſe hee is a man, is more to bee valued and eſteemed, then all the gold and ſiluer in the world. Well, whatſoeuer may bee ſayd of <hi>Marcellus</hi> for his clemencie, ouer thoſe whom hee had ſlain: or of the milde and humane ſpirit of the Emperour <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it to be very noble and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; yet is there no compariſon to bee made betwixt him, and the Emperour of heauen and earth, euen the God of the whole world: who, as the Prophet ſayth, is <hi>mercifull gracious, long-ſuffering, and of great goodnes.</hi> For if <hi>Mercie</hi> were not before him, and <hi>Grace</hi> behind him, if <hi>long-ſuffering</hi> ſtood not at his right hand, and <hi>great goodnes</hi> at his left: if theſe Peacemakers (as I may cal them) being qualities in his nature, did not mightily preuaile with him, why, ſo great is our ſinne, that the world could not ſtand, but had long ere this time periſhed like Sodome, and had beene deſtroyed, as was Gomorrah. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:132778:11"/>would you know, what vpholds the frame and ſtructure of the world? why, it is <hi>Mercy:</hi> would you know what vpholds the good eſtate of Iſrael, of our land? His <hi>Mercy:</hi> would you know what continues the dayes of our ancient mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Iſrael, our gracious Soueraigne, that as yet we cannot ſay of her, as was ſayd of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.7.</note> that her eyes haue waxed dimme in her head, or her natural force abated: but ſtil flouriſheth as the Palme tree, and groweth vp as a Cedar in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon? tis <hi>Mercy.</hi> In a word, you know the cauſe of the Goſpels continuance amongſt vs, that yet with freedome we may heare the ſound of it in our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and with peace behold the open faces of Gods Prophets, which bring vnto vs the gladde tidings of ſaluation: why wee enioy other bleſsings and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits in the land, and are not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from vs, by the violence and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine of forraine ſtrangers? it is his <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> his <hi>Grace,</hi> his <hi>long ſuffering,</hi> his <hi>great goodnes,</hi> that hee bare to thee, <hi>O Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> euen to vs, his owne people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23, 37. our Sauior Chriſt doth there challenge <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for great cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie,
<pb facs="tcp:132778:12"/>that hee had ſent Prophets, but ſhe had ſlaine them: and Apoſtles, but ſhe had ſtoned them. <hi>O Ieruſalem, Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them which haue beene ſent vnto thee: how often would</hi> I <hi>haue gathered thee together, euen as the hen gathereth her chickens vnder her wings, but yee would not?</hi> The hen was not more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ouer her yong ones, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was ouer you, ſayth the Lord: and my loue and kindnes, and louing kindnes was not once or twice, but <hi>often.</hi> Neither would I haue committed the truſt of you to any other, but <hi>my ſelfe would haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered you together.</hi> What loue and kindneſſe could I more ſhew, <hi>but you would not?</hi> I would (O Ieruſalem) but thou wouldſt not.</p>
               <p>How <hi>often</hi> beloued, hath the Lord wooed vs on this maner? how <hi>ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> hath the heauenly trumpet of his mercie ſounded in our eares? howe <hi>often</hi> hath the ſweete ſhowres of his mercie fallen vpon our heads, euen as aboundantly, as the Quailes vpon the Iſraelites? If you ſhould denie it, I would aske the ſtarres in the heauens, the beaſts of the
<pb facs="tcp:132778:12"/>earth, the foules of the ayre, and the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of the ſea, and all theſe would wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with me. <hi>How often</hi> hath the Lord cried vnto you in effect, <hi>Yarmouth, Yarmouth,</hi> thou that ſwelleſt in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of thy conceit, that ſayſt with <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea, Reu.</hi> 3. <hi>I am rich &amp; increaſed with goods, and haue neede of nothing:</hi> and therefore <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>enuie</hi> ſtriue which ſhall get the vpper hand, as the vnruly waues of the ſea encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter one another: wickedneſſe walkes vp and downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you without controlment, and iniquitie runs full ſea in the channels of thy ſtreets, and the courſe thereof can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſtayed. Sodome and Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah lie not in the duſt for greater abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, then are daily committed: thou Yarmouth, that art in this caſe, <hi>How often would</hi> I <hi>haue gathered you to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, euen as the hen gathereth her chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens vnder her wings, but you would not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Lord reaſons with vs (beloued:) Many fruits of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings haue you taſted of, both by ſea and by land: from time to time hath hee ſent home your ſhippes, ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with the riches of the Ocean, as if
<pb facs="tcp:132778:13"/>they came laden with treaſures from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt: for which, the Lord encreaſe not only plenteouſnes within your veſſels, but euen thankfulneſſe within your bowels. Many excellent and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inſtructions haue beene deliuered vnto you, by the mouths of his ſeruants, the Prophets. All this hath beene to this end, to gather you together vnto the Lord: his bleſsings temporall, and his graces ſpirituall, haue beene as two hands, to draw you home vnto him: but as yet, for ought wee ſee, you will not. Therefore looke vnto it: if the like ſhould befall you, as here to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> (either in this place by <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadnezzar</hi> and the Caldeans, or there, by <hi>Titus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37.</note> and <hi>Veſpaſian:</hi>) that your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhould entrench your towne, and enuiron you round about, that hunger and famine ſhould tirannize ouer your bodies, whereas now plentie ſits at your doores, to welcome your friends: that the ſword of ſome forraine Nation ſhould ſhorten your dayes, whereas now the ſword of good Magiſtrates is carried before you: if your houſes of pleaſure, ſhould become your priſons:
<pb facs="tcp:132778:13"/>if your louing wiues ſhould be deflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and your tender infants murdered in the ſtreetes before your faces: If this, or a greater euill ſhould befall, which the Lord in his mercie turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, beloued, is it not iuſt? ſhall wee challenge God of his equitie, or charge him of iniuſtice, and ſay: Lord, why haſt thou done this? ſurely no: many times (ſayth the Lord) would I, but you would not: for I am a God mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, gracious, long-ſuffering, and of great goodneſſe: but the more I was mercifull, the more you were ſinfull: the more I was gracious, the more you were graceleſſe: the longer I was in ſuffering, the longer were you in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and the greater I was in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the greater were you in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion: therefore, becauſe I then would, but you would not: perhaps now you would, but I will not. Bethink your ſelues of your eſtate preſent: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke your ſelues what may befall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>O Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (the elect Citie of God) moſt holy, moſt glorious, built vpon holie mountaines, no Citie in the
<pb facs="tcp:132778:14"/>world comparable thereunto,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum Nico. de Lyra gloſſ. ordina. Eſay</hi> 2. <hi>Mich.</hi> 4.</note> as well for the loftineſſe of the ſeate, for the temperature of the ayre, for the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the heauens, and fruitfulneſſe of the ſoyle: and yet all this ſerues not ſo much for the credit of it, as that <hi>The Scepter went forth from Sion, &amp; the word of God from Ieruſalem.</hi> It was the onely place of Gods onely worſhip: the Lord had a delight to haue his name there: neither had any more priuiledges, more teaching or prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, then they had: yet for all this, they wanted perſeuerance, they could not continue vnto the end: yea, theſe which ſhould haue bin ſchoolemaſters to al other Nations round about them for knowledge. Yet ſee the teſtimonie that God giues of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Ch.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Run to and fro in the ſtreets of Ieruſalem, behold now, &amp; enquire in the open places, if ye can find a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or if there be any that executeth iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; ſeeks the truth, &amp; I wil ſpare it, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Loe, my beloued, not a righteous man, not a faithfull ſoule (it ſeemes) found in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their princes, or among their people.</p>
               <p>Whereby we learne,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> that howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:132778:14"/>wee haue the word of God prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and the heauenly oracles of his will reuealed vnto vs, from the boſome of the almightie, by the mouthes of his Prophets, and other priuiledges and prerogatiues giuen vnto vs, which God hath not vouchſafed to other Nations: yet cannot wee challenge this priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and prerogatiue of perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. So likewiſe, the Churches of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, and of Epheſus, excellent priuiledges they had, and great prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues they were graced with, yet could they not perſeuere vnto the end.</p>
               <p>Well, the vſes in a word,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> that wee are to make hereof, are diuers: firſt, in that Ieruſalem, thus priuiledged and bleſſed, could not perſeuere, it ſerues to teach vs, that in any place which the Lord hath countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced with the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of his word, if the hearts of the people bee not ſet to obey, the Lord will giue no bleſsing vnto it. If prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching &amp; practizing bee not ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; if the Goſpel &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce walke not hand in hand; if Gods word, &amp; our workes; if the light of his Goſpel, and the light of our godly conuerſation
<pb facs="tcp:132778:15"/>be found aſunder: alas, wee may with <hi>Eſau</hi> deceiue our ſelues,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.</note> and thinke to haue a bleſsing, when wee ſhall hit vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a curſe. Therefore, let vs not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues with the outward ſound of the word, if the inward obedience of the heart bee abſent: though wee bring our Bibles to Church vnder our armes, it is not that will make vs good Chriſtians, if our hearts be not ſet to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey: but wee muſt ioyne the outward miniſterie of the word, and the inward obedience of the heart together: no ſooner muſt the Lord open his mouth, but wee muſt open our eares, &amp; drinke the ſound of his word, into the ſecrets of our harts, which may become migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and by the operation thereof, make vs fruitfull vnto ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> in that Ieruſalem could not continue &amp; perſeuere, it ſerues to teach vs, that wee which haue had the excellent benefit of his word, and by the beames of his glorious Goſpel, haue beene enlightned in the wayes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> wee muſt (as <hi>Paul</hi> admoniſheth vs) <hi>ſtandfaſt,</hi> and not bee as variable cloudes in the ayre, that are carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb facs="tcp:132778:15"/>with a tempeſt, but ſtedfaſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and confident, in the profeſsion of the Goſpel. For if wee prooue either faint-hearted, or faithleſſe hearted Chriſtians: if it bee ſayd of vs, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſayd of the Galathians:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ye did runne well</hi> in the race of Chriſtianitie, but now, yee ſlide backe: our end ſhall be worſe then our beginning: for it had beene much better that wee had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer learned the truth, nor knowne the way of righteouſneſſe, then after wee haue knowne and learned it, to returne with the dog to his vomit, and with the ſow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Non lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilegia, aut im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes poſsu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nos ab ira Dei eximere.</hi>
                  </note> in that Ieruſalem could not perſeuere, it teacheth vs that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: <hi>Wee which thinke wee ſtand, muſt take heede leſt wee fall:</hi> let vs not boaſt of thoſe priuiledges and bleſsings that God hath enriched vs with: for were they neuer ſo many, or neuer ſo great, Ieruſalem had more, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: yet, though ſhee was highly in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite with the Lord, and countenanced of him as the Empreſſe of the world, her glorie is here threatned to bee layd
<pb facs="tcp:132778:16"/>in the duſt.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 11.2</note> Let <hi>Nimrod</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie build a Citie, whoſe towres and turrets may reach vp into heauen: yet ſhall <hi>Babel</hi> bee <hi>Babel:</hi> the thing it ſelfe ſhall bee the confuſion thereof. The whore of Babylon may aduaunce her ſelfe in pleaſures,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 18.8.</note> and in the pride of her heart ſay, <hi>ſhe ſits as a Queene, and ſhal ſee no mourning:</hi> yet <hi>ſhall her plagues come at one day, death, ſorrow, and famine, and ſhee ſhall bee burnt with fire: for ſtrong is the Lord God, which will condemne her. Reu.</hi> 18.8. Therfore, if we aſſure our ſelues of the continuance of Gods fauour amongſt vs, by our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward proſperitie, or thinke to ſtand hereafter, as wee haue ſtood hitherto, wee are deceiued: for were we as deere and neere vnto the Lord, as Ieruſalem, or anſwerable vnto it, either for braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of buildings, commodities of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, ſtore of munition, to driue backe the force and fierce aſſaults of our enemies, yet are they not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to driue back the gun-ſhot of Gods diſpleaſure, when for our tranſgreſsion, hee entendeth our deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> ſeeing wee ſee Ieruſalems
<pb facs="tcp:132778:16"/>eſtate to bee this; it teacheth vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our prayers and ſupplications vnto GOD, for this ſpeciall bleſsing of perſeuerance: for what profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a man,
<note place="margin">Simile.</note> to ſayle a long voyage proſperouſly, and with ſucceſſe, if at length hee makes ſhipwracke, beeing ready to enter into the hauen? So, what will it auayle vs (my brethren) ſayling in the full ſea of Gods bleſsings, and in the flouds of his aboundant mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, with the winds of proſperitie, and before we come to our iourneyes end, make ſhipwracke of fayth and a good conſcience? It is not ſufficient for vs that wee <hi>runne,</hi> but we muſt ſo runne, as wee may <hi>attaine.</hi> It will not auaile vs to <hi>begin well,</hi> if wee doe not continue to the end: if wee haue begunne in the ſpirit,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.3.</note> there is no perfection to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for in the fleſh. That ſeede is in vaine caſt into the ground, whereof a man filleth not his boſome in the time of harueſt: and the profeſsion of the Goſpel is ill begunne, and to no purpoſe, except we perſeuere vnto the end.</p>
               <p>Now, it may be demanded,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Why did
<pb facs="tcp:132778:17"/>the Lord looke for ſuch meaſure of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> perſeuerance, and other fruits in Ieruſalem, more then in the Caldeans?
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> The reaſon is, Becauſe he had beſtowed greateſt bleſsings vpon them: and the Lords maner is, where he beſtowes greateſt bleſsings, there he lookes for greateſt obedience: and where there is greateſt preaching, there doth hee expect greateſt practiſe. That Parable of the fig-tree,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 31.6.</note> planted in a vineyard, ſerues fitly for the illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof: <hi>A certaine man</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>had a figtree planted in a vineyard,</hi> and becauſe hee had planted it, <hi>he came and ſought fruit thereon, but found none. Then ſayd he to the dreſſer of the vineyard: Lo, this</hi> 3 <hi>yeere haue</hi> I <hi>come, and ſought fruit thereon, &amp; hauc found none: cut it down, why keepeth it the ground barren?</hi> This vineyard, beloued, is the Church of God: the fig-tree, though it bee there meant of the eſtate of the Iewes, yet by it may bee vnderſtood the eſtate of euery ſeuerall ſoule: the planter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is Chriſt, the dreſſers are his ſeruants the Prophets. Nowe (ſayth Chriſt) I haue planted a fig-tree, great cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:132778:17"/>therefore that I ſhould haue fruit of it. Well, any time theſe three yeres haue I come and ſought fruit thereon, but haue found none. Neither is it onely fruitleſſe it ſelfe, but it makes the ground barren and fruitleſſe likewiſe. Surely, my purpoſe is, it ſhall bee <hi>cut downe,</hi> and caſt into the fire.</p>
               <p>O Lord (beloued) an happie thing were it, if in our vineyard wee had no ſuch vnprofitable fig-trees; if in our Church wee had no ſuch vnprofitable profeſſors: vpon whom Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and miniſters haue beſtowed coſt, and of whom, no doubt, the Lord hath expected and wayted for, not <hi>three yeres,</hi> but many yeeres, the fruits of his bleſsings: but alas, wee deceiue his expectation: long hath he thought for, and ſought after the fruits of his Goſpel, but loe, nothing but weedes of diſobedience ſpring vp amongſt vs. What will bee the end of this? Surely, we may iuſtly feare the like iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that befell to the fig-tree: <hi>Cut it down: why keepeth it the ground barren?</hi> Wee may (I confeſſe) bee ſuffered to grow for a time, to flouriſh for a ſeaſon, yet
<pb facs="tcp:132778:18"/>vtter deſtruction wil happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the end. We know heretofore, how the Lord hath dealt with vs, for wee haue playd the hypocrites with him, and therefore hath hee made the earth, and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures thereon, to play the hypocrites with vs. The Lord hath expected the fruits of our obedience, but behold, it is like vnto a ſhadow, ſomething in ſhew, but nothing in ſubſtance; or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as <hi>Ephraims</hi> righteouſneſſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Oſe.</hi> 6.4.</note> like to the <hi>morning dew:</hi> ſo wee (in former yeeres) haue expected the fruits of the earth from him, yet haue wee beene partakers of the curſe that <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeakes of:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 31.40.</note> That <hi>thiſtles haue growne in ſteade of wheate, and cockle in ſteade of harley:</hi> ſo as the huſband-man ſorrowed and ſighed within himſelfe, when hee ſaw no better fruit of his labours.</p>
               <p>Thus hath the Lord cauſed the earth to deceiue our expectation, becauſe wee haue deceiued his: and though now on a ſodaine, hee hath equally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided the pipes and cunduites of his mercie, and opened the windowes of heauen, and hath ſent downe a <hi>graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous raine,</hi> vpon the ground of the good
<pb facs="tcp:132778:18"/>and of the bad, of the <hi>iuſt,</hi> and of the <hi>vniuſt,</hi> filling our boſomes with abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of bleſsings, that our vineyards clap their hands, and our fields doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and ſing: yet let vs beware that this ſodaine proſperity and plenty, bee not to fat vs againſt a day of ſlaughter.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore conſider our eſtate what wee are, and what wee haue beene, euen a people <hi>bleſſed of the Lord:</hi> but wee may ſpeake of our ſelues, as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſpeakes of a certaine countrey, that <hi>ex ſiccitate lutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ex imbre puluere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c.</hi> drought hath cauſed durt, and raine hath ſtirred vp duſt amongſt vs: for what hath the ſunſhine of his mercies? but cauſed vs to lie in the mire of our abominations: and what hath the moyſture of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? but euen dryed vp the fountaine of grace in vs: ſo as wee are giuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to worke tranſgreſsion with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe: the increaſe of his bleſsings haue encreaſed our iniquities; and the aboundance of his mercies haue brought forth aboundance of ſinne in vs: for what haue wee, but in ſteade of obedience, rebellion? in ſteade
<pb facs="tcp:132778:19"/>of knowledge, ignorance? Is there no complaint of oppreſsion to be heard in our ſtreetes? doe not rich men grinde the faces of the poore, plucking their skinnes from their bodies, and their fleſh from their bones, as the Prophet ſpeakes? Is not one man readie to pull out the throat of another, vrging, and vſing extremitie, rather then a good conſcience, in matters of law? Is there no ſwearing, and forſwearing? no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of the Sabboth amongſt vs? doe not <hi>Abſaloms</hi> adulteries runne for meriments in our age? and haue wee not thoſe, fitter for the companie of Sodomites, then for the ſocietie of Chriſtians? and behold, yet, and yet greater abominations then theſe? Are theſe the fruits of the Goſpel? is this the iſſue and effect, that Gods word hath wrought in vs theſe fortie yeeres? haue we anſwered the Lords expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the ſmalleſt meaſure of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as hee hath anſwered our deſires, in the greateſt meaſure of his mercies? Surely no. Oh beloued, what then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines for ſuch vnprofitable fig-trees? <hi>Cut them downe, cut them downe</hi> (ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:132778:19"/>the Lord) burne them in the fire.</p>
               <p>So much for the firſt poynt, the perſon exhorted, and the inſtrue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereof.</p>
               <p>Nowe followeth the ſecond poynt, namely, the thing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe.</head>
               <p>THe Prophet doth here touch <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to the quicke,
<note place="margin">Quid la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uandum. Fons vita</note> when hee comes to the <hi>heart:</hi> which, (as Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions ſay) is the fountaine of life: it is the firſt thing that liueth, and the laſt thing that dieth in a man. The heart is like an Inſtrument: if it bee in tune, and well ſtruug,
<note place="margin">Dulce melos.</note> it makes a <hi>ſweete me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody:</hi> but if it bee out of tune, all the parts and powers of minde and body are out of courſe. Or as the ſtone of <hi>Scyros,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. lib.</hi> 36. <hi>Cap.</hi> 17.</note> if it bee caſt whole into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, floteth, and ſwimmeth aloft, but if it be parted and diuided, it ſinketh to the bottome: ſo is it with the heart, ſo long as it bee kept whole and vndi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, why, it ſwims, and all things runne currant with it: but if broken
<pb facs="tcp:132778:20"/>or diuided, it ſinketh like lead. It may bee compared to the apple of a mans eye, which will be troubled with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle moate: ſo is the heart tender of it ſelfe, and will bee diſquieted with a rebellious affection: or looke euen as a ſteele-glaſſe is bright and pure, yet the breath of ones mouth will dimme it: ſo is the heart, a thing in it ſelfe bright and pure, yet are there many wicked and contagious vapours in the ſoule, that dimme and obſcure the integritie thereof.</p>
               <p>When God looked downe from heauen, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Hee ſaw the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man was great on the earth:</hi> and did God behold but the earth onely? ſurely yes, hee tooke a view of mans heart alſo; and there hee found the <hi>heart,</hi> and not the heart onely, but the <hi>thoughts</hi> of the <hi>heart,</hi> and the <hi>imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of the <hi>thoughts:</hi> the mother, her daughters, and their children <hi>euill,</hi> and not onely euill; but <hi>onely</hi> euill, and cuil <hi>continually.</hi> Aboue all things (ſayth the Prophet) man hath an <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythfull heart,</hi> as deepe as the deepe ſea, nothing can ſound it: as wide as the
<pb facs="tcp:132778:20"/>wide world, nothing can contain it: as large &amp; ſpacious as hell it ſelf, who can find it out? If a man poſſeſſed as much ground, as euer the deuil ſhewed the ſon of God fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the high mountaine; if hee had the whole world, yet could mans heart containe another &amp; if he had two worlds in his poſſeſsio, yet the heart of man would bee caſting for a third: therefore it is worth the noting, that which <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> is reported to haue obſerued in himſelfe, when by wraſtling, he had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a fal in the ſand, and ſeeing the impreſsion of his body therin, was thereby (as it ſeemes by his words) brought into conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that a ſmal parcell of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but a ſpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of earth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but the whole world, were it much wider the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is, ſufficed not his couetous heart. Wel, whatſoeuer the hart of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, I leaue vnto God, the ſearcher of all harts to examine: &amp; whatſoeuer <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedons</hi> couetous heart was, &amp; the harts of thoſe, which in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of <hi>Noah</hi> were ſwept away with the waters of the floud: yet here we find, <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> hath a <hi>wicked hart,</hi> &amp; ſo wicked, that vnleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:132778:21"/>it bee purified, purged, and waſhed with the waters of repentance, <hi>deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon deſtruction</hi> is proclaimed againſt it, <hi>verſe</hi> 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe.</head>
               <p>Where firſt of all wee note, that our repentance muſt bee like the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of <hi>Niniueh,</hi> it muſt begin with the King: hee muſt firſt ariſe from his throne, and throw away his coſtly robes, and couer himſelfe with ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and aſhes, and then proclaime the like to his ſubiects and inferiors: that is to ſay, the <hi>heart</hi> which ſits in the body, as a king in his throne, and hath all the inferior powers at commaund, when <hi>Ionas</hi> ſhall denounce iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and the Lords miniſters proclaime re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, it muſt firſt rouze and raiſe vp it ſelfe: and when that begins, the inferiour parts are eaſily brought to order: therefore ſayth the Prophet, <hi>Waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe:</hi> not thy face, or thy hands, or thy feete, or thy vpper garments, but thy <hi>heart, O Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Our hearts may bee compared to
<pb facs="tcp:132778:21"/>the rudder of a ſhip, or the ballance of a clock: the ſhip (wee know) is a great and an vntoward veſſell; and if it bee left to it ſelfe vpon the ſeas, it runnes to a thouſand dangers: but let the rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be well guided, and the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die thereof, with all that belongs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, is directed without hazard: ſo, if the heart go aright, it goeth not alone, but all the parts and powers of the ſoule and body, immediatly follow in the ſame ſafetie: euen as a clock,
<note place="margin">Simile.</note> if the ballance thereof ſtirre, all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruments and weights follow in a good courſe: but if that ſtand ſtill, euerie one of the reſt goe out of order: ſo, let our hearts moue and ſtep for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the courſe of Chriſtianitie, all the inſtruments and members of the body will goe onward likewiſe: but if the heart ſtayes, the body ſtirres not, but ſtanding ſtill, is the apter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any corruption.</p>
               <p>Well,
<note place="margin">Firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</note> the inſtructions that wee learne from hence, are diuers: firſt, in that wee muſt beginne with the heart, it teacheth vs, that true repentance ſtandeth not in outward behauiour,
<pb facs="tcp:132778:22"/>in outward ceremonies, or in a ciuill kind of life: but it muſt ariſe from the <hi>heart.</hi> Wee cannot chaſe wickedneſſe from our eyes, from our hands, from our tongues, or from our feete, if firſt it bee not chaſed from the heart: for the eye may bee wicked, the hand may bee wicked, the tongue may bee wicked, and the feete wicked, but the <hi>heart</hi> is the ſeate of <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> it is a fountaine of iniquitie, the ſtreames wherof ouer-runne the whole body: therefore to good purpoſe is that of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vena ſcin datur cordis. Ioel</hi> 2.13.</note> Rend your hearts, and not your gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and turne to the Lord your God:</hi> becauſe it was the maner of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times, when any were poſſeſſed with griefe and diſcontent, to <hi>rend their garments,</hi> manifeſting by their outward behauiour, their inward ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: as in the example of <hi>Dauid</hi> for <hi>Saul,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.11. and for his ſonne <hi>Abſalom,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.31.</note> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.31. of <hi>Ioab</hi> for <hi>Abner,</hi> and of other. Now, leſt this ceremonie, or ſuch like, ſhould bee rather of faſhion, then from the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the heart, <hi>Ioel</hi> diſclaimes from them, as things which the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth
<pb facs="tcp:132778:22"/>not, if the puritie of the mind, and ſinceritie of the heart bee abſent. It is not outward ſanctification, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward holineſſe, outward behauiour, that the Lord requires, but the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and purging of the heart from ſinne: <hi>For God ſeeth not as man ſeeth:
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Prou.</hi> 15.11.</note> man looketh on the outward appearance, but the Lord beholdeth the heart:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Waſh thy heart, O Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might here by the way, take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to fight a battell with hypocrites,
<note place="margin">Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</note> whom we may compare to boat-men, that look one way, but row another: or like to Mercuries Images, that poynt the way to others, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſtand ſtill and ſtirre not one foote: or like to ſtage-players, which for an houre or two, ſeeme to be greatſtateſ-men, but the play being ended, they are as baſe companions as they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: or like vnto the Carbuncle, which hath a ſhew of fire, but no true fire: ſo they; a ſhew of zeale, but no true zeale:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.27.</note> or as thoſe <hi>paynted Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,</hi> beautified to the eye, but within, full of rottenneſſe and corruption. Theſe will <hi>ſeeme religious amongſt you,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132778:23"/>though <hi>not refraine their tongues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 1.26.</note> but <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue</hi> their owne <hi>hearts;</hi> whoſe <hi>religion</hi> (by the iudgement of the Apoſtle) is <hi>vaine.</hi> But to leaue them (becauſe my purpoſe was but to take them by the lap of their garments at this time, for a remembrance onely) let vs that will bee Chriſtians in deede and ſinceritie, bee warie that we play not the ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with our ſelues, thinking that outward puritie and ſinceritie ſtand for currant in the ſight of God. It is the pureneſſe and ſanctimonie of the heart <hi>onely,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance muſt be, nou cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris, ſed cordis. Eiuſdem capitis.</note> that the Lord requires: we may pray with the Phariſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11. and kiſſe Chriſt with <hi>Iudas, Mat.</hi> 26.49. and offer ſacrifice with <hi>Cain, Gen.</hi> 4.3. and faſt with <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 21.9. and humble our ſelues with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab, verſ.</hi> 27. and preſent an Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>Ananias, Acts</hi> 5.2. and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the teares of <hi>Eſau, Gen.</hi> 27.38. yet all theſe are nothing, if the <hi>heart</hi> be not <hi>onely</hi> deuoted and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated vnto God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe.
<note place="margin">Second inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>
               </head>
               <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, in that he ſayth, <hi>Waſh thine
<pb facs="tcp:132778:23"/>heart from wickedneſſe,</hi> wee ſee howe lothſome a thing it is in the ſight of God, to haue a <hi>wicked heart,</hi> an heart not ſanctified and vpright before him. An happie thing were it, if wee could bethinke our ſelues, what an enemie we carrie about with vs in our breaſts, when we haue <hi>wickednes</hi> in our hearts. It is like <hi>death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Malitia.</note> which hauing once ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed vpon the heart, all the members of the body are immediatly captiued: ſo, let the heart bee <hi>wicked,</hi> and the whole body is wicked: for <hi>out of the aboundance of the heart,</hi> the head deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, the hand executeth, the tongue ſpeaketh, the eye ſeeth, the foote wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth:
<note place="margin">I. <hi>King.</hi> 15.30.</note> and euen as wicked <hi>Ieroboam made all Iſrael to ſinne,</hi> ſo the wicked heart makes the whole body to ſinne.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſhould euerie one of vs pray with good King <hi>Dauid:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note> Create in mee, O Lord, a cleane heart, and renew a right ſpirit within mee.</hi> Wee muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodge our hearts of this great <hi>euill,</hi> and make them the wagons and chariots of the Spirit, wherein hee may ſit to guide our whole body: and the priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which hereby wee ſhall reape, is
<pb facs="tcp:132778:24"/>ſingular:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 8.14</note> for (ſayth Saint <hi>Paul) So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as are led by the Spirit, are the ſonnes of God.</hi> Now, the Lord hath giuen vs our hearts and bodies, to bee <hi>reſting places</hi> for the holy Ghoſt, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſhould take delight to ſeate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. But alas, the Spirit ſits in the ſtreetes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 19</note> like the Leuit that came from <hi>Gybeah,</hi> and no man receiues it into the houſe of his heart: nay, wee chooſe rather to make them dennes for the diuell, ſtore-houſes of ſinne, and euen a Dagon of all iniquitie. Should it be thus with Chriſtians? God forbid: the Lord hath giuen thee a body, to bee the <hi>temple of the holy Ghoſt:</hi> ſhalt thou now take this body of thine, and make it the body of an harlot? God forbid: the Lord hath giuen thee hands, as organs, to performe the neceſſarie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions belonging to thy welfare, ſhalt thou now diuert them to an ill vſe, and make them inſtruments of murder, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, rapine, &amp; oppreſsion? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid: the Lord hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee a tongue, an excellent benefit of nature, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey vnto thy brother the ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of thy mind, both for the prayſe
<pb facs="tcp:132778:24"/>and glorie of God, and for thy profit and benefit in thy trade of life: ſhalt thou now make it a tongue of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, vnchaſtitie, curſing, ſwearing, and forſwearing? God forbid: the Lord hath giuen thee eyes to behold his creatures vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of the heauens, &amp; the ſuperficies of the earth, to behold the admirable workes of the almighty, in the frame of the world: and they are as two lights, for without them, the whole body ſhould be poſſeſſed with darknes: now, dareſt thou attempt to make them inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to ſollicite the heart with vncleannes? or make them windowes of vanity, by beholding the beauty of the ſtrange woman? nay, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let vs ſay with <hi>Ioh,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 31.1.</note> I haue made a couenant with mine eyes, not with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to behold a virgin.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Foedus pepigera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis meis, &amp;c. Pro.</hi> 23.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thus haue you heard, that the Lord hath giuen vs an heart, that we might, as <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſedome requires, <hi>giue it vnto the Lord</hi> againe: hee hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs a body, that wee might, as <hi>Paul</hi> requires, <hi>offer it vp vnto him</hi> againe. All powers and parts of both hath God giuen vnto vs, that wee ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:132778:25"/>dedicate them to him againe: but alas, wee beſtow them vpon Satan, ſinne, and the pleaſures of the world. <hi>Iehu</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not the temple of <hi>Baal</hi> more baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then wee vſe our hearts, making them cabbins of vncleane ſpirits, full of deadly ſinnes, whereas they ſhould bee veſſels of holineſſe and honor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs therefore in the Lords feare, ſupplant this bitter roote of <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> in our <hi>hearts,</hi> and plant in them the graces of the ſpirit, that the heart may bee as a ſweete garden furniſhed with vertues, as with fragrant flowres, that hee may ſay of it, as elſewhere hee ſpeakes of Sion: <hi>Here will I dwell, for I haue a delight herein:</hi> ſo ſhal he which created it, haue it; he that gaue it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it againe; and he which preſerues it in this life, may preſerue it for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Third inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> in that he ſayth, <hi>Waſh thine heart from wickedneſſe,</hi> it giues vs to vnderſtand, that ſinne is a corruption: for the word here which the Prophet vſeth,
<note place="margin">Laua: Ablue.</note> is a borrowed ſpeech, taken from the maner of thoſe, which are
<pb facs="tcp:132778:25"/>wont to rinſe or waſh any thing that is filthie or polluted: for our hearts being as ſinkes or channels apt to receiue any filth and corruption, are to bee purged and ſcoured with the beſome of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and waſhed with the teares of contrition, that they may not appeare loathſome vnto God. The leproſie of Naaman, 2. King. 5. a greeuous lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie:
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>14</label> yet when hee had waſhed himſelfe ſeuen times in the waters of Iordan, his fleſh came againe like the fleſh of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle child, and he was cleane. So likewiſe wee haue all a more greeuous leproſie then euer Naaman had, and are more lothſome in the ſight of God then euer he was in the ſight of men:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.5</note> for <hi>there is nothing whole within vs,</hi> but woundes, ſores and ſwellings, and our hands are full of bloud, yea from the crowne of the head to the ſole of the foot, we are nothing but blemiſhed with iniquitie,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.16.</note> and ſtained with corruption: therefore ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Waſh you, make you cleane:</hi> wee muſt with Naaman to the waters of Iordan, and there waſh our ſelues ſeuen times and we ſhalbe <hi>cleane</hi> Neither muſt we follow our owne car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:132778:26"/>reaſon; for then wee will iudge <hi>Pharpar</hi> and <hi>Abanah,</hi> riuers of Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, better then all the waters of Iſrael: but we muſt take the direction of the <hi>man of God,</hi> and Iordan is the place muſt doe vs good. If we conſult with fleſh and bloud, about the matter of our conuerſion and waſhing away of ſinne, we ſhall neuer be cleane: but if we follow the aduice of Eliſha or any of Gods miniſters, were pur leproſie worſe then Naamans the Aſsyrian, the waters of Iordan would <hi>waſh</hi> it away; were our hearts like Ahabs chariot, 1.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 22.38.</note> 
                  <hi>Kings</hi> 22. euen embrued with bloud and filthines, yet would they be cleane, being <hi>waſhed</hi> in the poole of Samaria. Were we eyther <hi>ſicke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.3.</note> or <hi>blind,</hi> or <hi>halt,</hi> or <hi>withered,</hi> and had neuer ſo many diſeaſes, or neuer ſo much diſtraction in our limmes, yet if we <hi>wayte for the moouing of the water,</hi> and ſtep into the poole of Betheſda, and there <hi>waſh</hi> our ſelues, we ſhalbe recouered: were our ſinnes like crimſin,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 1.</note> yet they ſhall be as white as ſnowe, and were they as red as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as white as wooll. This is the great benefit that wee ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:132778:26"/>reape and receiue after our baptiſme &amp; regeneration in the waters of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as Ionas in the waters of the ſea, wherin being throughly purged &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from our corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, by the bloud of the <hi>immaculate Lambe,</hi> we ſhall with Ionas receiue a newe commiſsion, and be inueſted into our former credit and fauour with God. For this ſame corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinne, which lyeth in the heart <hi>vnwaſhed</hi> away, is a bird, which (as I may ſay) ſings two maner of notes, or hath two maner of calles. It eyther cals to vs, or it cals to the Lord: when to vs, it cals for repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance; when to the Lord, it cals for vengeance. So that, though ſinne lyeth ſhrowded full low in our hearts, and wickednes be harboured in the ſecrets of our ſoules, yet is thy ſinne like the ſinne of Sodome, <hi>the cry of it is exceeding great:</hi> for they are ſo many in number, ſo diuers in nature and differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in kinde, that being in thy heart, they are like vnto a ſort of fierce Lions and cruell Tygres in a den,
<note place="margin">Beaſtes of diuers kinds.</note> which cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together. And therfore, if thou la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureſt not to empty thy ſelfe of them, and open thine care vnto them, when
<pb facs="tcp:132778:27"/>they <hi>crie</hi> and call vnto thee for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the Lord will open his eares, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they call to him for vengeance.</p>
               <p>It is lamentable to conſider (yet it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath beene, and I thinke it will be) that men are poſſeſſed with ſmalleſt care in matters of greateſt danger. The infection or corruption of the bodie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man will labour to purge &amp; waſh away, but the corruption of the ſoule, &amp; the <hi>wickednes of the hart</hi> no man regards: nay, after ſinne committed (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet fitly notes) No man ſaith, What haue I done? O miſerable &amp; wretched ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I am, what haue I done? though it be an aſpiring kind of wickednes, as that of the Niniuites:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ionds</hi> 1.2</note> aſcending, cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and being feathered with the wings of preſumption flies vp into the court of heauen, euen daring to ſhew it ſelfe in the preſence of the moſt high: though it extends to the annoyance of the earth below, to the prouocation of the heauons aboue, to the puniſhment of all the creatures in and betweene them both: nay though it ſtrikes and ſtrikes with a double hand at the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of God himſelfe, yet no man ſayes,
<pb facs="tcp:132778:27"/>
                  <hi>What haue I done?</hi> O Lord, (beloued) a long time haue wee beene acquainted with ſinne, but can our acquaintance gaine vs no experience of ſinne? will you euer looke vpon the pleaſure and profite that ſinne brings vnto you; but will you neuer haue an eye to the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and ſubtiltie thereof? Indeed wee make much of it:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eaſola voluptas, ſolame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> mali. Aenei.</hi> 3</note> we nouriſh it in the ſecrets of our harts, and keep it warme in the inwards of our ſoules: wee are as loth to forſake ſinne, as Iacob was to forſake Beniamin: and to depart from iniquitie, as Lot was to depart from So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: but ſhall we neuer looke into the miſchiefe that enſueth of it? When ſhal we once be wiſe? They ſay that no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement is ponderous or waightie in his proper place: as for example, we feele not the weight of the aire, although we liue within the circle and compaſſe of it. Suppoſe a man ſhould lie in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the ſea, it would not offend him with any preſſure or burdenſome waight, although it ill annoyed him otherwiſe: ſo is it in the eſtimation of ſinne: wee liue and wee lie in it; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las wretches that we are, we feele not,
<pb facs="tcp:132778:28"/>no, we feele not the weight and burden thereof, how it euen preſſeth our ſoules vnto condemnation. Sinne is not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie vnto vs, by reaſon of the inclination of mans will thereunto, which greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth ingurgitate &amp; readily ſwallow vp a whole ſea of abomination. It may ſeeme ſtrange which is written of the nature of thunder, that it bruiſeth the tree, yet breaketh not the bark, it crac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the blade, but neuer hurteth the ſcabbard: ſuch a thing is the nature of ſin, it wil bruiſe &amp; wound the heart, but neuer harm the eies, or the eares, or the hands; it wil pearce and afflict the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but neuer hurt the outwarde man; it is euen a plague vnto the ſoule, &amp; yet a pleaſure vnto the body. Well, the time wil not permit to ſet out ſinne as it deſerues, &amp; to acquaint you more with the nature of it, although I would to God wee were leſſe acquainted with the vſe, &amp; leſſe affected with the deſire thereof: yet ſo violently are our head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong affections caried and rauiſhed, that we adde ſinne to ſinne, and ioyne them in a league of friendſhip, &amp; when we haue ſo done, we lay iniquitie vpon
<pb facs="tcp:132778:28"/>ſinne, wickednes vpon iniquitie, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion vpon wickednes, and tranſgreſſion vpon rebellion, and nothing els but an heauing, and heaping vp of confuſion vpon confuſion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.2.</note> as if Nimrod were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, &amp; Babel againe to be built, the towers wherof might reach vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtarres.</p>
               <p>Well beloued, let vs lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of ſinne as low as wee will, and build as ſtrongly thereupon as we can, as if wee were aſſured, that the hand of Gods iudgements ſhould neuer raſe it vp; yet no doubt we ſhall find, that it is nowe high time for vs to leaue our ſinnes, ſeeing wee ſee the Lord begins to leaue vs for our ſinnes. It is nowe high time for vs, not to <hi>waſh</hi> our hands with Pilate, but our hearts with Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; to chaunge our Morian skinnes, to put off our ſtained and defiled gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, to entertaine repentance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſoules, ſeeing that euen nowe wee feare the rewarde of our impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the portion of iniquitie to bee ſhared out for vs. If euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was needfull, ſurely nowe much more neceſſitie enforceth, and
<pb facs="tcp:132778:29"/>time it is for Abigal (if ſhe reſpect her owne ſafetie) to ariſe and meete Dauid with a preſent to appeaſe his wrath,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.</note> for it ſeemes hee is now at hand with <hi>his ſword girded vpon his thigh:</hi> though not to lade our Aſſes as ſhe did, with two <hi>bottles of wine, with frailes of raiſins,</hi> and <hi>a ſheepe readie dreſſed,</hi> or ſuch like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion: but to lade our bodies and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full carkaſſes, which wee haue vſed as Aſſes to beare the huge burthen of our ſinnes with ſackcloth and aſhes,
<note place="margin">Saceus &amp; ieiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium ſunt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae.</note> with faſting &amp; mourning, which are the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of repentance to withſtand his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Let our eyes be as 2. bottles of wine, to cary with vs, the teares wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we may drinke, to comfort vs in the aſſurance of Gods mercies, &amp; our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; contrite harts as preſents which the Lord wil haue reſpect vnto, and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue kindly at our hands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 35.</note> &amp; lay his ſword downe which he hath taken vp againſt vs. and bidde vs <hi>returne in peace vnto our houſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh that I could poſſibly preuaile thus farre with you, to poſſeſſe your ſoules with the conſideration of this point. Though this ſodaine oportunitie of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb facs="tcp:132778:29"/>were not offred vs, yet let vs examine our eſtate, and we ſhall finde, that (alas) we are not ſinners of yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; we are not newly entred into Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans ſchole: but we are of a great ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: for in ſinne our mothers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued vs, in iniquitie they brought vs foorth, and wee drewe corruption from their breaſts; all which, as wee haue growne with them, ſo they haue growne with vs. We haue long and ouerlong traced the footeſteps of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and troden the paths of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice; wee haue tyerd our ſelues, and ſurfeted our ſelues with the workes of abomination: we are not fallen of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance (alas) as our forefathers, which knewe not the Goſpell; but willingly &amp; wilfully haue we brought our ſelues into the habite of ſinne, into the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſinne, into the cuſtome of ſin, and within the compaſſe of Gods moſt fearefull iudgements, to ſeaze vpon ſoule and body, vnto condemnation; and not vpon our ſelues onely, but ſuch is the corruption thereof, that it hath ouerſpred the face of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, of the earth, and ouerunne all
<pb facs="tcp:132778:30"/>the creatures, that euen they for our ſin muſt one day come to iudgement. O then how needfull is it, that with Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem wee ſhoulde <hi>waſh</hi> our <hi>wicked heartes</hi> from this corruption with the teares of repentance, that ſhee might ſit in thy <hi>heart,</hi> and with her ſtrong ſighes and grones breake the heauens which are hardned againſt thee, and draw downe the Lords louing fauour to thy ſoule. If the infant in the cradle cries for milke; if the Lion in the forreſt cries for food becauſe they want it: how ſhould it moue vs (my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to ſend vp our cries for the fauour of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue it not! The teares of our eyes being ſhed in true contrition for our ſinnes, will bee as little meſſengers to the great and angrie God of heauen and earth, to entreate a truce betwixt him and vs his creatures, and as gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhotte, will batter downe the partition walles of our ſinnes, and cauſe his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing countenance to ſhine vpon our ſoules. Let vs therefore in the feare of God make experience of this, and though for the time it may ſeeme bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as Aloes vnto the fleſh, yet is it
<pb facs="tcp:132778:30"/>wholeſome and medicinable vnto the ſoule. And looke as it was the manner of ancient times, when trouble or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines befell to any, they preſently cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for women and others who were tender harted and skilful in mourning, to cauſe them mourne the better: ſo we which would faine learne to repent and lament for our ſinnes, and know not rightly how; let vs haue recourſe vnto the booke of God, and there may we behold the teares ſtanding in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalems eyes, and in the eyes of Marie Magdalene,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1</note> &amp; of Anna the wife of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kanah, that their weeping might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our weeping, their griefe prouoke our griefe, their paſſions moue our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections with the like lamentation and ſorrow for our ſinnes.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>So much for the thing required,
<note place="margin">Quorſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecond point,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Waſh thine heart from wickednes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now followes the third, which is the End,
<note place="margin">End.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That thou mayeſt beſaued.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:132778:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>J</hi> Doubt not,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vt ſalua ſis. Verſes</hi> 5.6.7.8.</note> but the trumpet blowne in the land, and the <hi>crie,</hi> which ſaid vnto them of Iudah, <hi>Aſſemble your ſelues together, &amp; get you into ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g cities;</hi> and the ſtandard ſet vp in Sion, and the plague threatened to be brought from the North,
<note place="margin">Iuterfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note> and the Lion that ſhould come from his den, and the <hi>Drie wind in the high places of the wilderneſſe,</hi> and that ſuddenly; (for it ſhould be as a tempeſt and ſwift) for <hi>his horſes are lighter then Eagles;</hi> might eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them of imminent and preſent danger, except they had the hearts of the Leuiathan, as ſtrong as ſtones, or as hard as the nether milſtone, not to receiue any impreſsion; or their ioynts tough as Elephants, that nothing could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end them. Therefore their danger th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eatning ſuch extremitie, it was more then time to take ſome courſe for their owne ſafetie.</p>
               <p>The Poet notably deſcribes the feare that Aeneas and they of Troy were in,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aenci.</hi> 3</note> and the great ſpeed they made to eſcape the danger of the Cyclops.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Praecipites metus acer agit quocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132778:31"/>
                  <l>Excutere, &amp; ve!tis intendere vela ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>When they ſaw the companie of giants cluſtring vpon the ſhore,
<note place="margin">Aetni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> fratres.</note> reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the ſtrength and fortitude of mightie Okes, or loftie Cypreſſe trees, that their verie looks threatned deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, it was no time for them of ſtay, but ſpeedily to hoyſſe vp their ſailes,
<note place="margin">Parebia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> &amp; nimbly to betake them to their oares; rather then the giants ſhould offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to them, <hi>they offer violence to the ſea,</hi> and haſten away.</p>
               <p>The only courſe that Icruſalem hath to preuent this imminent diſtres, which was euen at their ſhore ready to aſſault them, is ſwiftly to ſaile away in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of repentance: euerie man to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelfe to his oares of true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition and inuocation vnto God, to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour painefully in the ſea of their ſinful hearts (though they be well <hi>waſhed</hi> &amp; drenched with the waues thereof) for their owne <hi>ſafetie</hi> and preſeruation. Waſh thine hart from wickednes,
<note place="margin">Ve Deus te in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorem recipiat.</note> 
                  <hi>That thou mayeſt be ſaued.</hi> In the handling of which I will firſt ſpeake of the ſence of the words ſecondly, of the vſe.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, the word in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:132778:32"/>ſignifieth,
<note place="margin">Salutem, open<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, opitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem. A verſu quinto.</note> either ſafetie, helpe, or aide: and here it may fitly beare a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſence; firſt, by the relation of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter going before: for in the former part of this Chapter many iudgements are exemplified by many figures to come vpon Ieruſalem by Nabuchadnezzar, and the Chaldeans, who ſhoulde cut them downe with the ſword, &amp; <hi>lay their land waſte.</hi> Now this being ſo, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſtirs vp Ieruſalem to repentance, that ſhe may be <hi>ſaued:</hi> that is to ſay, In this common calamity and iudgement which is to fall, yet that ſhe may be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and ſafe from the touch thereof, and bee reſtored to the fauour of God: and therefore, that the faithfull among them ſhould not deſpaire, but rather lift vp their heads and cheare themſelues with a hope of <hi>ſafety</hi> in time of danger, as alſo to croſſe the crooked generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hypocrites, ſhewing that there is no way to appeaſe Gods wrath by any ſhiftes, but by true conuerſion which muſt beginne at the hart. Or thus, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> that thou mayeſt bee <hi>ſaued</hi> in the day of iudgement by the redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, becauſe <hi>without repentance there
<pb facs="tcp:132778:32"/>is no ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And ſo for the ſence. The vſe followes.</p>
               <p>In time of daunger, or of proſperity,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>vſe.</hi>
                  </note> or whenſoeuer, is any thing ſweeter vnto vs then our life? or more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious then the breath of our owne no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils? Why (ſayes the Deuill) when hee enformed againſt Iob,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Skinne for skinne, and all that euer a man hath, he will giue for his life.</hi> Be it a life of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, miſerie, and vexation, yet natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally wee loue it better then death. <hi>Tanti eſt contemplatio coeli &amp; lucis ipſius, &amp;c.</hi> So wee may beholde heauen and the light thereof, in our owne eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is ſo much worth, that we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to endure any miſerie for it. I will appeale to no other witneſſes at this time, then to the Gibeonites,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſuah</hi> 9.24.</note> who did that which they did, and became ſlaues to the hoaſt of Iſrael. <hi>For feare of their liues</hi> they were content to endure any ſlauerie and bondage, ſo as they might eſcape with life. And therefore that action of Cleombrotus may ſeeme ſtrange, that reading Platoes diſcourſe of the immortalitie of the ſoule, fell from the top of an high wall, of purpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:132778:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>to breake his neck, the ſooner to attaine to immortalitie.</p>
               <p>Howſoeuer, this action of his, as one ſayes, was <hi>Potius magnè factum, quàm bene factum,</hi> a great act, rather then a good acte. It ſeemed likewiſe that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaemenides the vnfortunate compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Vliſſes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Comes infoelicis Vliſſis. Virgil. Spargite me flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergite ponte.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 19.</note> little regarded the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of life, and thought it rather a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to die, ſo it might bee <hi>manibus homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m,</hi> in ſome manlike manner. And that of Elias in the ſacred volume ſauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth much to this purpoſe, It ſufficeth, Lord, take away my ſoule from me, let me not liue any longer to bee eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that miſerie that Iezabel hath thretned vnto me. Well, howſoeuer, to let them paſſe that are ſo weary of their deareſt friend, ſure it is, <hi>euerie thing in nature deſireth being,</hi> from the greateſt to the ſmalleſt: and this great benefite repentance brings with it, life in the middeſt of death, <hi>ſafetie</hi> in time of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie, preſeruation againſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, deliuerance in time of danger. <hi>O Ieruſalem,</hi> if, when Nabuchadnezzar ſhall come as a fierce Lion from his den, &amp; the Chaldeans as cruell Tygers
<pb facs="tcp:132778:33"/>to deuoure thee; when mine indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be thy portion to drinke, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſtruction vpon deſtruction ſhall befall for the execution of my ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance: yet if thou wilt be <hi>ſaued</hi> when others muſt be deſtroyed, here's thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, <hi>Waſh thine heart from wickednes.</hi> So you ſee the Prophet reaſoneth with them <hi>a fructu poenitentiae,</hi> from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites ariſing from repentance.</p>
               <p>To giue you the taſte of it in a word: If the ſeas which are as a girdle to this Iland (enuironing and encompaſſing the ſame about) were at our command, or that the Lord ſhould put the raines and gouernment of the mightie waters into our handes, that wee might rule them as wee liſt for the ſubuerſion of our enemies; or that our land were wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with braſſe, and ſtrengthened with the ſtrongeſt defence againſt our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar of Spaine, and our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the Caldeans: Yet would not all this make ſo much for our <hi>ſafetie,</hi> as if we had repentance in our hearts, a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall antidote againſt any iudgement. In deed we feare the forces of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine foes, and we may iuſtly: but our
<pb facs="tcp:132778:34"/>greateſt enemies are our home-bredde ſinnes. We ſtand quiuering and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnder the rod of his Iudgement, the feare whereof hath ſo poſſeſſed vs, that we runne hither and thither, and are almoſt at our wits end, as if there were no God to goe before the ſhields of Iſrael. What is the cauſe hereof? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, our guilty conſciences doe accuſe vs, and we can not but confeſſe, howe iuſt our deſtruction is. For were wee penitent ſinners, and at peace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God, we ſhould not neede to feare what man can doe vnto vs: but till ſinne be remoued out of our hearts, and our iniquities as rebels, caſt out of our ſoules; vntill wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come penitent for the manifeſt &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold tranſgreſsions of our liues, alas, we muſt yet liue in feare of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard; neyther may we feare Spayne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but euen the heauens, and the ſtarres in the heauens, to ſight againſt vs,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.</note> as they fought againſt Siſera; the earth, and the creatures on the earth, to plot out our ſubuerſion: for the Lord will vſe them as his men of warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, and make them at vtter defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb facs="tcp:132778:34"/>with vs. Nay, wee may feare our hands, which we account as our dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friends: for he can make them as the hands of Saul,
<note place="margin">I. <hi>Samu.</hi> 31.4.</note> euen inſtruments of our owne confuſion.</p>
               <p>If therefore wee will haue peace in our land betwixt Spayne and vs, wee muſt labour for peace in our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces betwixt God and vs. If we would haue Gods Iudgements remoued from vs, wee muſt labour to remooue our ſinnes, which are the cauſe of them, and then will the Lord paſſe his word vnto vs, that wee ſhall bee <hi>ſaued.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 16 17.</note> To depart from euill</hi> (ſaith Salomon) <hi>is a fortreſſe and a bulwarke, to preſerue the righteous from Iudgements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the whole world with engines of warre threatened our confuſion, yet if wee were engrafted into Chriſt, and made one with him, (betwixt whome there is nowe as great a ſeparation as Abrahams gulfe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.</note> by reaſon of our manifold ſinnes and tranſgreſsions) there is no doubt, but his louing coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and mercifull eye ſhould euer be vpon vs, &amp; his right arme ſtretched out for our defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Wil any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hurt the
<pb facs="tcp:132778:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132778:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:132778:36"/>apple of his owne eye, and not rather to be tender ouer it? why, we are <hi>as the apple of the Lordes eye.</hi> Will a man caſt off or diſhonour the ſignet of his right arme? why, we are his ſignet: wil a man vſe violence to the wife of his own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, who is one fleſh with himſelfe? why we are the Lords <hi>ſpouſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1.</note> &amp; he hath made vs <hi>one</hi> with him, and therefore may looke for protection and defence at his handes, and not for ſtrokes and violence, as if our God were a ſtranger vnto vs, &amp; had neuer giuen vs pledges of his loue. Thus as you ſee the danger that we may iuſtly feare by reaſon of ſinne, ſo likewiſe the comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that we may haue, if we become penitent for our ſinne. Therfore which of theſe two makes greateſt for our <hi>ſafetie,</hi> iudge you.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> to ſpeake of <hi>ſaluation</hi> by the redemption of Chriſt (who gaue his bloud once for our ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſome) it is a thing generally deſired of vs all,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.5. <hi>heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.</note> nay many make claime vnto it, as <hi>Eſau</hi> did vnto the bleſsing, &amp; yet muſt go without it. The way that leadeth thereunto is narrow,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13.</note> and ſcarſe one amongſt a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:132778:36"/>findes it: we are as lame creeples, we cannot ſo much as get to the <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gate,</hi> except we be <hi>carried;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 3.2</note> much leſſe into the temple it ſelfe, vnleſſe our lameneſſe be taken away. There is but one way vnto it, and that is by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: he that ſeekes <hi>ſaluation</hi> &amp; Gods kingdome any other way, takes a wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g courſe: it will not be got either with pleaſure or profit: all the gold of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir, the treaſures of Ezekias, or the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Salomon will not buy it: onely repentance will ſo farre preuaile, <hi>that thou mayſt be ſaued.</hi> And therfore Chriſt told the Iewes (who thought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues priuiledged, and therfore condemned the Galileans) <hi>Except you repent,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.3.</note> ye all ſhall likewiſe periſh.</hi> Therefore beare this principle in mind, for it ſtands as firme as the pillers of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance there is no ſaluation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>And thus much for the <hi>Exhortation</hi> it ſelfe and the parts thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, the perſon exhorted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, the thing required.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, the end.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:132778:37"/>
               <p>Now followes the reaſon:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Howe long ſhall thy wicked thoughts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne within thee?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THis is an argument vſed by way of complaint; wherein (if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, we obſerued theſe 5. poynts.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the circumſtance of time, wherewith the argument was enforced: <hi>How long?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the thing which the Lord complaynes of: they are <hi>thoughts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the qualities: they are <hi>Wicked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, their continuance: they <hi>remayne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, the place of their abode is, <hi>within vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the foure latter, though we may compare our ſelues to the ſea, into which all the riuers of the earth runne, &amp; is neuer the fuller: ſo though all the inſtructions in the Scripture be applyed vnto vs, yet many are neuer the better, and therefore neceſſary to handle theſe ſeuerally,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Diuiſion. </seg>
                  </label> which would miniſter excellent matter vnto vs: yet, let it ſuffice, to faſten onely vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:132778:37"/>ſence of the Prophet, and deliuer from them ioyntly ſuch inſtructions,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Coniūctū </seg>
                  </label> as flow from the words themſelues for our edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
               <p>But firſt, for the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance of time, <hi>How long?</hi> A word of great conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce:
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Quovſ{que} </seg>
                  </label> It implyes thus much:</p>
               <p>Is it not ſufficient (O Ieruſalem) that I haue borne with ſinne ſo long, and doe you thinke me ſtill able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it? Haue I but hitherto winked at your iniquities, and will you yet and yet vexe my righteous ſoule? Is this the fruite that my long-ſuffring brings forth in you? Wert thou borne ſinful, and wilt thou dye ſinfull? Is there no place for repentance? <hi>Howe long ſhall thy wicked thoughts remayne within thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Lord reaſons with Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem and with vs. And ſurely it is fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that our ſinne ſhould growe to ſuch an height, and iniquitie waxe ſo ripe, that the Lord ſhould thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine of it, <hi>Howe long?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When God ſends Iudgements vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, &amp; the fingers of his wrath faſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either on our bodies or goods; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peſtilence came with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angry God of
<pb facs="tcp:132778:38"/>heauen, to attach our ſinfull and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious carcaſſes, and the bodies of our ſonnes and daughters; when we feared to draw our breath in the ſtreetes, leſt we ſhould haue drawne our confuſion, and not an haires-breadth there was betwixt vs and death; when the vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate mouth of the graue ſtill craued for more, and neuer thought it had i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and ſpared not to ſwallow vp our ſweeteſt comforts; when day by day we followed our friends with wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, our neighbours with mourning, &amp; our nereſt kinſfolks with lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation, to bring them the way of all fleſh; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death was as a tyrant amongſt vs,
<note place="margin">Mors tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nns, Cicero.</note> and the peſtilence as an vnmercifull ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier that ſpared none: then (beloued) what did we? Surely, we cried &amp; cried, <hi>How long, Lord,</hi> Lord, how lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wilt thou abſent thy ſelfe hiding thine eyes from beholding, and ſtopping thine eares from hearing the wordes of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint? <hi>How long, Lord,</hi> wilt thou giue vs gall to drinke, and fill our ſoules with bitterneſſe, as with wormwood: <hi>Lord, how long, how long, Lord,</hi> ſhall it be thus or thus with vs?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:132778:38"/>
               <p>Thus we preſſed the eares of the Lord with our <hi>how long,</hi> and he heard it. <hi>He</hi> looked downe from heauen and beheld the ſorrow of the ſonnes of men vpon earth. He commanded his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell to ſtay his hand, clearing our ayre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infection, and ſeaſoning our ioynts with health. Thus did the Lord helpe vs, when we could not helpe our ſelues. But (alas) he cryes and complaynes of our wicked <hi>thoughts,</hi> ſinfull liues, and adulterous conuerſations; but we giue him not the hearing.</p>
               <p>Loe, beloued, our vnequall hearts, and the vnkindneſſe wherewith we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite him, who ſo kindly hath dealt with vs. Let. God complayne, but we will not complayne. He cryes, <hi>Howe long?</hi> We cry with Salomons ſluggard, Not long inough: Yet a little more ſleepe, a little more ſlumber, a little more folding of the armes together.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 1.15. <hi>ioſ.</hi> 15.18.</note> And as Achſaph in the booke of Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, was importunate for riches, and neuer thought her ſelfe ſatiſfied: ſo is it with vs; when wee haue committed one ſinne, we thinke we may commit a ſecond; and that being done, we will
<pb facs="tcp:132778:39"/>yet venter vpon a third. If wee liued one hundreth yeeres, we could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to liue another, ſo wee may liue to ſinne; &amp; when we haue liued two, yet we thinke it not enough. Well, let vs in the feare of God ſlake the thirſty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereof, and labour to ridde our ſelues of it: for he that hath feweſt ſins, in the day of Iudgement ſhall find hee hath too many: and let vs weigh the Lords cauſe in our owne ballance; that as we thinke, we may iuſtly complaine, when the weight and burden of his iudgementes are vpon vs: ſo let vs thinke the Lordes complaint equall, when the weight and burthen of our ſinne is vpon him.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1.14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> this <hi>How long</hi> is like Cyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius to pull vs by the eare, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh vs how we ſpend our time: for God wil haue a reckning of euery idle houre that we ſpend; therfore it ſhould teach vs to walke circumſpectly as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15.</note> 
                  <hi>redeeming the time,</hi> that what time ſoeuer heretofore hath beene ill ſpent, wee may haue an eye to the time to come that it may be well ſpent: for we know not whether we haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:132778:39"/>dayes reſpit allotted vnto vs, as the Niniuites had: but ſure an happy thing is it for him that hath time &amp; place for repentance, and wofull will it be when the whole courſe of our life is ſpent in vanitie and profaneneſſe; and in the ende and vpſhotte thereof the Angell of God ſhall anſwere vs, <hi>Time ſhall bee no more.</hi> Eſau had a time when hee might haue repented, but being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlipt, <hi>he had no place for repentance,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.17.</note> though he ſought the bleſsing with teares.</hi> Theſe times are not allotted for the bodie, but for the ſoule.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.11.</note> And now is the time not of pleaſure or delight, but of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if euer we will haue it. Therefore let <hi>tempus vitae</hi> be <hi>tempus poenitentiae;</hi> let the time of our life bee the time of our repentance.</p>
               <p>So much for the circumſtance of time <hi>How long:</hi> Now it followes:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How long ſhall thy wicked thoughtes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine within thee?</head>
               <p>HE y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the eare, doth not he heare? &amp; he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath created the eye.
<pb facs="tcp:132778:40"/>doeth not he ſee the thoughts of the heart? Man can but iudge of actions and outward appearances onely; but <hi>the Lord knoweth the heart.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Penetrat Deus vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad ine timos re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſus cordium. Pſa.</hi> 139 15.</note> There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hidden from God, eyther in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or earth, or within the reynes and hearts of our bodies, or of the loweſt deſtruction, but he ſeeth it <hi>with eyes ten thouſand times brighter then the Sunne. My bones are not hid from thee</hi> (ſayth Dauid) <hi>though I was made in a ſecret place, and faſhioned beneath in the earth.</hi> And in the 94.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe </seg>7</label> Pſalme, ſpeaking howe the wicked ſmote the Lords people, and troubled his inheritance, ſlewe the widdowe, and murthered the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, it went to his heart to heare them ſay,
<note place="margin">Non reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picit Iah.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord ſhall not ſee</hi> it: As if their wickedneſſe could ſhrowd it ſelfe from the all-ſeeing eye of his eternall Deity. They are not onely our actions and words, that are apparent vnto the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie,
<note place="margin">Thoughts</note> but the <hi>thoughts</hi> of our heart, whether they be good, or euill.</p>
               <p>Thus the LORD ſawe Ieruſalems <hi>thoughts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wicked.</note> and he beheld them <hi>wicked:</hi> according to that of the Prophet, <hi>The Lord knoweth the thoughts of men,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.</note> that
<pb facs="tcp:132778:40"/>they are but vayne,</hi> or, <hi>vanitie it ſelfe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſe</hi> 11 <hi>Quod ipſae ſunt vanitas, traiectio.</hi>
                  </note> And Gen. 6.5. <hi>The Lord ſawe the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of the thoughts of</hi> mans heart <hi>euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The thoughts of the heart are like vnto a gadding ſeruant, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhould employ him ſelfe to his maſters buſines at home, he runneth and rangeth after his own pleaſure: ſo when our <hi>thoughts</hi> ſhould bee attendant to the heart, for the ſeruice of God, they are here and there, and abroad, after their owne vanities: nay, many marre them,
<note place="margin">Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis: ſic Cal. ſuper ter.</note> as fooliſh parents doe their wanton chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, by too much cockering and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring of them, and by giuing them too much liberty without reſtraint; but ſuffer them to followe their owne luſts, winding themſelues ſo much into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with vs, that they preuayle ſo far, as from an vnchaſte imagination, the body is carried into an vnchaſte action; and from a proud &amp; an angry thought, comes forth many times a blaſphemous othe: yea, they will vrge and preſſe vs onward vnto euill: wee can no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhake off a <hi>wicked thought,</hi> but with the Egyptian flye it will light vpon vs
<pb facs="tcp:132778:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>againe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 6.14.</note> Therefore as God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Noah to pitch the Arke within &amp; without, that no water ſhould get in: ſo ſhoulde wee pitch the arkes of our ſoules, that no violent and diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thoughtes might ruſh in to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe vs: or as wee hedge our vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yardes from wilde beaſtes, ſo ſhoulde we hedge our heartes with the graces of the Spirite, from vnruly and vnta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med affections, not to giue them the leaſt ground of aduantage; but to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue that heauenly principle of an heathen Poet;
<note place="margin">Principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is obſta.</note> 
                  <hi>Withſtand beginnings,</hi> becauſe they may bee compared to Panthers, who haue ſweete ſmelles, but deuouring mindes; and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite of a <hi>wicked thought</hi> may ſeeme pleaſing and delightſome, but in the ende it deuoures like a two edged ſworde.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Captains. Mat.</hi> 8.9</note> Wee ſhould bee maſters of our thoughts, as the Centurion was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his ſeruantes, that when wee ſay to a <hi>wicked thought,</hi> Goe, it ſhould depart: and when to a good thought, Come, wee ſhould then embrace it. But if with deceyte,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 9.23</note> like the Gibeonites, they get themſelues within vs, and like
<pb facs="tcp:132778:41"/>hypocrites, fayne themſelues otherwiſe then they are, let vs with the hoſte of Iſrael, ſet them <hi>to hew wood,</hi> and <hi>to draw water;</hi> employ them to the ſeruileſt and baſeſt duties, or rather, ſlay them out of hand, leſt the Lord ſlay vs: for they be not the actions or words onely of the oppreſſour, adulterer, or proud man, that ſhall be puniſhed; but he will <hi>ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the proud,</hi> or any other whatſoeuer, <hi>in the imaginations of their hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus cordis ipſorum. Luk.</hi> 1.51.</note> &amp; for our <hi>thoughts</hi> wee muſt come to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Well, the Lord heere deales with Ieruſalem, as a Phyſicion with his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, who preſcribes ſuch a medicine for their maladies, that hee would not any corruption ſhould bee left behind, whereby they might either ſeeme loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vnto him, or deceyue themſelues with a vayne hope of ſecuritie, when there is no ſuch matter.</p>
               <p>For what though the whole world had iudged well of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or though by any outward ceremonies they had ſeem'd conformable, if ſtill the <hi>thoughts</hi> of iniquitie had
<note n="*" place="margin">Pernoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, hoſpitari, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare: ſic enim hebraice ſignificat.</note> 
                  <hi>lingred</hi> in their wicked hearts, which would haue bene as an
<pb facs="tcp:132778:42"/>inward corruption feſtering in a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and in the end haue brought greater miſerie vpon them?</p>
               <p>Where note,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtru∣ction. </seg>1</label> that (when we ſee any Iudgement ready to fall vpon vs) in the matter of our repentance, wee muſt deale with ſimplicitie, and not to dreame of any ſhift or vayne excuſe, to beare vs out againſt any Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; whatſoeuer we may doe with men, yet muſt we deale in ſingleneſſe of heart with the Lord: for there is neyther <hi>thought,</hi> any ſhift, excuſe, or deuice, but the Lord is inward vnto it; which if he once perceyues, it enforceth him to a further reuenge.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.6.</note> It was the caueat which Paul gaue to the Epheſians: <hi>Let no man deceiue you with vayne words: for, for ſuch things, the wrath of God commeth vpon the children of diſobedience.</hi> If men eyther excuſe ſinne in themſelues, or mocke at the Iudgements of God, the anger and wrath of God in the violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt maner comes vpon them.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtru∣ction. </seg>2</label> let vs learne from hence, that though wee reforme ſome fewe ſinnes, and reſtrayne our ſelues from outward offences, whereof the world
<pb facs="tcp:132778:42"/>condemnes vs, yet can we not promiſe our ſelues ſecuritie, if we haue any <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thoughtes</hi> raigning and remaining in our harts. And therefore becauſe mans nature is ſo ſubiect to corruption drawn from Adam, that the brighteſt fire hath ſome ſmoke, the cleareſt fountain ſome mudde, and the pureſt hart ſome infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wee muſt in the ſincereſt manner that we may, wholly reſigne our ſelues into the Lords hands, and commit the ordering, diſpoſing, and ſanctifying of our thoughts to his good will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; knowing that in him lyeth all our ſafetie &amp; ſecuritie from all iudgements; and for our ſelues, were wee as iuſt and vpright as Daniel, yet might wee ſay with him, <hi>Shame</hi> (Lord) <hi>and confuſion belongs vnto vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, let vs learne,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtru∣ction. </seg>3</label> not to thinke it a ſmall matter, when any olde ſinne or corruption <hi>remaines within vs.</hi> For if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any thing be dangerous, ſurely this is moſt daungerous, when a ſinne that ſprouted vp in vs thirtie or fortie yeeres agoe, &amp; ſtill the ſame ſinne <hi>remaines</hi> in our hearts,
<note place="margin">In medio tui.</note> and lurketh in the <hi>inwards</hi> of our ſoules, ſurely, it is now growne to a
<pb facs="tcp:132778:43"/>great tree, &amp; not eaſily to be pluckt vp. For it is the nature of ſin, when cuſtome giues it any encouragement, firſt it is an <hi>egge;</hi> ſecondly, a <hi>cockatrie:</hi> thirdly, a <hi>ſerpent;</hi> fourthly, a <hi>fierie flying ſerpent.</hi> For as it <hi>remaineth,</hi> it keeps not at a ſtay, but it groweth vp, &amp; gets hart, ſtrength and encouragement, that it fares like a ſleepie Lyon,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7</note> which if a man begins to rouze, is ready to fly in his face. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs cruſh the heads of our <hi>wicked thoughts,</hi> while they are but little ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and not ſuffer them to <hi>remaine</hi> in our hearts ſo long, leſt at length they get ſtrength to ouer-maſter vs.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, by the tenor of this argument wee may ſee, how the Lord is grieued with the delay of repentance in any ſinner:
<note place="margin">Simile.</note> we know in our owne ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie affaires (either in following matters of law, or when wee haue any ſuites &amp; requeſtes to exhibite to princes or men of ſtate) <hi>delay breeds many dangers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mora trahit pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculum.</note> and makes vs that we either go without the thing that we ſue for, or els we obtaine it with great difficulty and charge: after the ſame ſort, if any deſires this heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly promotion, which all the kingdomes
<pb facs="tcp:132778:43"/>in the world cannot purchaſe, and bee ſlacke in following the ſuite thereof, to thinke as Naaman thought of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Iordan,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 5</note> that other waters may be as good, &amp; ſo another time as meet, <hi>and ſhall not to morrow bee as to day, &amp;c.</hi> ſurely he ſhall eyther go without it, or els obtaine it with great difficultie: for the <hi>longer</hi> that we <hi>remaine</hi> in ſinne, the further off will the Lord be from vs, yea ſo farre, as it ſhall be hard to find him; and the more ſinnes that a man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth, the more walles of braſſe are built and made vp betwixt God and vs, that the cries of our ſinfull hearts can not haue paſſage vnto him, nor his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies vnto vs. Were it not much better then (beloued) to <hi>ſeeke the Lord while he may be found,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay</hi> 55.</note> and to call vpon him while he is neere?</hi> to put vp our ſupplications into the hands of this heauenly Prince while hee now paſſeth by vs, then to ſtay and delay till he ſhuts himſelfe vp in his chamber of preſence, and then will not open vnto vs? Oh that wee could once bee wiſe and prouident for our owne ſaluation! When Abel offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſacrifice, he brought the firſt fruits
<pb facs="tcp:132778:44"/>of his ſheepe, and the fatte of them to offer vp:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4</note> 
                  <hi>And the Lord had reſpect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</hi> And ſhall wee thinke to ſpend the <hi>firſt fruites</hi> of our age, and the prime of our yeeres in ſinne, and the ſeruice of the Deuill; &amp; when we haue thus ſpent the ſtrength, ſap and greenneſſe of our youth; and grow old and withered, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like <hi>brands in the fire</hi> of ſinne,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>waſted and conſumed to ſtumps,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks; and then offer vp our old, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous, broken and ſhattred ſacrifices vnto God? ſhall we thinke (I ſay) the Lord will regard them? or that he will thus be mocked at our hands? Surely no. Our ſafeſt courſe (beloued) will then bee, not to grieue the Lord with delayes, that he ſhould iuſtly complain of vs, as of <hi>Ieruſalem: How long ſhall the wicked thoughtes remaine within thee?</hi> Is it not yet enough? <hi>Are ye not content to grieue men onely, but you will grieue mee alſo? &amp;c.</hi> But rather forthwith whiles wee are in our beſt ſtrength,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
                  <hi>before the euill day commeth,</hi> to ſeaſon our greene veſſels with the liquor of his ſpirit, euen with holineſſe and ſanctimonie of life, and to thinke the prime of our yeeres,
<pb facs="tcp:132778:44"/>and (as it were) the maidenhead of our youth, in the pureſt and holieſt maner, to bee better beſtowed on the Lord, who hath promiſed himſelfe to bee a moſt louing and faithfull husband vnto vs, then vpon the Deuill, which is our profeſſed enemie, and ſeekes our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw euerie way. O let vs conſider how brittle a ſtaffe we leaue vpon, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we truſt vnto our old age, which when it breakes, the ſplinters &amp; ſhiuers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will wound vs. If we repoſe any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to the houre of death for Gods fauour, we tread but vpon yee; which if it be molten with a little heate of Gods anger, alas, wee ſinke into the gulte of deſtruction. Indeed many are blinded in giuing credite to Sathan, when hee ſaith vnto them, <hi>Ye ſhall not die,</hi> or <hi>the time is not yet, &amp;c.</hi> thinking that Gods mercie wil waite vpon them when their eyes ſhall be cloſed vp, or obtaine that at the houre of death, which they haue contemned all their life: but let vs for our partes labour for it, euen while it is called to day, yea while the Lord cals, and ſayes vnto vs as hee ſaid to Adam, <hi>Where art thou?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.9.</note> &amp; neuer colour nor cloke
<pb facs="tcp:132778:45"/>our filthines with the <hi>Figge leanes</hi> of our deuiſes, or ſhrowd our ſelues in the <hi>thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets</hi> of our <hi>wicked imaginations;</hi> for then we ſhall ſhew our ſelues of what houſe we come: but rather endeuour to bee <hi>new creatures</hi> in Chriſt the <hi>ſecond A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam:</hi> yet let it repent vs that wee haue deferred the time ſo long, and ſuffered ſinne to grow to ſuch a height, to the greater offence of our heauenly father, and to the greater hazzard of our owne ſaluation: and as he hath thought long for our turning vnto him; ſo let vs think long for his turning vnto vs, that there may be amity, league, and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip betwixt God and vs, and then ſhal we liue without feare of any forraigne enemy;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 14 14.</note> yea we may then <hi>hold our peace, for the Lord will fight for vs,</hi> and put all our enemies vnto the ſword: hee will make vs returne into the court of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with palmes of honour in our hands, and crowns of victory vpon our heads; and the whole Trinitie ſhall with one voice ſay, Amen, for the confirmation of our eternall happines. Then ſhall we haue no more wars, nor rumors of wars to diſmay vs; no more enemies to feare
<pb facs="tcp:132778:45"/>vs, no feare to grieue vs, no griefe to trouble vs, no trouble to diſquiet vs, no ſickneſſe to diſtemper vs, or death to diſſolue vs; but life in him who liueth for euermore. The Lord poſſeſſe out ſoules with a deſire of it, and giue a bleſſing to that which hath beene deliuered. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
